A Guide to the Papers of Joseph C. Cabelle and the Cabell Family
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Joseph C. Cabell and the Cabell Family 1731-1917
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-111
ca. 2400 items
Hartwell Cabell
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Cabell family papers were loaned to the Library by Mr. Hartwell Cabell of New York City, New York, and "Edgewood," Warminster, Nelson County, Virginia, with the major collection arriving in 1910, and additions at various times up to 1948.
The Library purchased the collection from James Self in 2001.
Scope and Content
The Cabell Family Papers consist of ca. 2,415 items (71 four-inch Hollinger boxes and one oversize box, filling ca. 25 linear feet of shelving), ca. 1731-1917, correspondence, diaries, account books, financial and legal papers, and other material. They are chiefly the papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell (1778-1856), planter, political leader, and statesman of Amherst (now Nelson) County, Virginia. There is a considerable quantity of material generated by other members of the Cabell family, including William Cabell, William D. Cabell, Nathaniel Francis Cabell, Mayo Cabell, Joseph L. Cabell, and Philip B. Cabell.
Some topics of interest in these papers include: nineteenth-century Virginia life, and the politics of the period ( Joseph C. Cabell served in the state legislature for nearly thirty years); agriculture; slavery; travels in England, France, Holland, and Italy from 1802-1806; an outline of a course of reading for the education of young men, prepared by Thomas Jefferson and St. George Tucker; the founding and early years of the University of Virginia ( Joseph C. Cabell served on the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia and as Rector); social life; and of course, the Cabell family itself. Prominent correspondents include: John Quincy Adams, R. A. Anderson, W. H. Benade, E. Benson, Samuel R. Betts, C. Bolling, P. A. Bolling, Richard Bolling, Tom Bolling, William Brent, Jr., R. A. Brock, Annie Cabell, Hartwell Cabell, William Cabell, William H. Cabell, William M. Cabell, John C. Calhoun, A. K.Campbell, Dabney Carr, Edward Carrington, Paul Carrington, William Cabell Carrington, Landon Carter, Henry Clay, George Clinton, John Coalter, John Hartwell Cocke, W. R. C. Cocke, Isaac A. Coles, D. Conway, R. Cralle, Peter V. Daniel, Jr., Walter R. Daniel, John D. Dickinson, L. C. Draper, Lewis Dubois, Baron Dubose, William Temple Franklin, Peter Gansevoort, Gessner Harrison, D. J. Hartsook, J. B. Hayword, George Hinkley, H. H. Hite, Alexander von Humboldt, John Jay, Thomas Jefferson, Joseph Johnson, Frank Keck, Arthur Lee, Richard Henry Lee, William Lee, Edward Livingston, D. H. London, J. R. McClelland, William Holmes McGuffey, B. G. McPhail, James Madison (Bishop), James Madison (President), Walkill Malcolm, John Marshall, John B. Minor, James Monroe, Charles J. Morris, Gouverneur Morris, Richard Morris, John Singleton Mosby, Wilson Cary Nicholas, Thomas Nelson Page, H. A. Powers, George Wythe Randolph, John Randolph, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Thomas Mann Randolph, William Cabell Rives, A. Sinclair, L. I. Singleton, Alexander Spotswood, James Stephenson, Andrew Stevenson, P. D. Sutton, Philip Tabb, James Tallmadge, John Taylor, Abraham Ten Broeck, Charles Thompson, George Tucker, Henry St. George Tucker, St. George Tucker, John Tyler, Robert Van Rensselaer, George Van Schaick, Edwin C. Venable, William Walker, J. H. Wallace, George Washington, James Webb, William Wirt, C. V. Woodson, and William Yates.
A card index to correspondents (through about 1852) found in this collection is available in the Manuscripts Department as is a calendar (prepared by Frances Elizabeth Harshbarger and completed to 1836 only) of part of the collection, and a copy of N. F. Cabell's
Early History of the University of Virginia as Contained in the Letters of Thomas Jefferson and Joseph C. Cabell
. A biographical sketch of Joseph C. Cabell from the
Dictionary of American Biography
is included in this guide.
There are a number of related Cabell collections owned by the Library: Accession numbers 383, 1495, 2791-a, 2791-b, 3021, 3021-a, 3073, 3119, 3845, 4606, 5136, 5542, 5644, 5970, 6038, and 7579
.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically except that in the post-Civil War years accounts or graphs of business material or of correspondence covering a period of years are filed under the earliest date on the folder.
Container List
- 1706-1800 Aug (Box Box 1)
- 1800 Sept-1803 Apr (Box Box 2)
- 1803 May-1806 May (Box Box 3)
- 1806 Jun-1807 Jul (Box Box 4)
- 1807 Aug-1808 Dec (Box Box 5)
- Account Books 1808-1809; 1809 Jan-1809 Jun (Box Box 6)
- 1809 Jul-1810 Dec (Box Box 7)
- 1811 Jan-1812 Aug (Box Box 8)
- Box 9 1812 Sept-1813 Jul
- 1813 Aug-1814 Jul (Box Box 1 0)
- 1814 Aug-1816 Nov (Box Box 11)
- 1816 Dec-1818 Dec (Box Box 12)
- 1819 Jan-1820 Mar (Box Box 13)
- 1820 Apr-l821 Dec (Box Box 14)
- 1822 Feb-1823 Jul (Box Box 15)
- 1823 Aug-1824 Oct (Box Box 16)
- 1824 Nov-1825 Aug (Box Box 17)
- 1825 Sep-1826 Dec (Box Box 18)
- 1827 Jan-1827 Dec (Box Box 19)
- 1828 Jan-1828 Dec. (Box Box 20)
- 1829 (Box Box 21)
- 1830 Jan-1831 Jul (Box Box 22)
- 1831 Aug-1832 Apr (Box Box 23)
- 1832 May-1833 Feb (Box Box 24)
- 1833 Mar-1833 Dec (Box Box 25)
- 1833 Mar-1833 Dec (Box Box 25)
- 1834 Jan-1834 Sept (Box Box 26)
- 1834 Oct-1835 Feb (Box Box 27)
- 1835 Mar-1836 Jan (Box Box 28)
- 1836 Feb-1837 May (Box Box 29)
- 1837 Jun-1839 May (Box Box 30)
- 1839 Jun-1841 Feb (Box Box 31)
- 1841 Mar-1842 Apr (Box Box 32)
- 1842 May-1844 Feb (Box Box 33)
- 1844 Mar-1845 Dec (Box Box 34)
- 1846 Jan-1846 Dec (Box Box 35)
- 1847 Jan-1848 Sep (Box Box 36)
- 1848 Oct-1850 Mar (Box Box 37)
- 1850 Apr-1851 Apr (Box Box 38)
- 1851 May-1852 Sep (Box Box 39)
- 1852 Oct-1853 Nov (Box Box 40)
- 1853 Dec-1854 Sept (Box Box 41)
- 1854 Oct-1855 Feb (Box Box 42)
- 1855 Mar-1856 May (Box Box 43)
- 1856 Jun-1857 Aug (Box Box 44)
- 1857 Sep-l858 Aug (Box Box 45)
- 1858 Sep-1859 (Box Box 46)
- 1860-1862 (Box Box 47)
- 1863-1865 (Box Box 48)
- 1866-1867 (Box Box 49)
- 1868-1869 (Box Box 50)
- 1870-1873 (Box Box 51)
- 1874-1875 (Box Box 52)
- 1876 (Box Box 53)
- 1877 (Box Box 54)
- 1878 (Box Box 55)
- 1879 (Box Box 56)
- 1880 (Box Box 57)
- 1881 (Box Box 58)
- 1882-1883 (Box Box 59)
- 1884-1888 (Box Box 60)
- 1889-1891 (Box Box 61)
- 1892-1909 (Box Box 62)
- 1910-1920, n.d. (Box Box 63)
- Miscellaneous School Papers, 1870-1880, n.d. (Box Box 64)
- Genealogy and Miscellaneous (Box Box 65)
- Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box Box 66)
- 1913-1914, n.d., Bound Volumes (Box Box 67)
- n.d., Bound volumes (Box Box 68)
- Scrapbook [of William Cabell?], 1806-1882 (Box Oversize)
- Scrapbook of newsclippings, 1838-1839 (Box Oversize)
- Scrapbook, 1865-1867 & 1891-1893 (Box Oversize)
- Photostat of a letter, n.d.; (incomplete) (Box Oversize)
- Novier: Memoire Sur Les Ponts Suspendus (Box Oversize)
- Scrapbook, n.d. (Box Oversize)